<document xml:lang="sme" id="no_id"><header><title>No mining in Nussir despite area development plan approval / Sártnit ja artihkkalat / Sámediggeráđđi / Organisašuvdnastruktuvra / Sámedikki birra  / Sámediggi - Sametinget</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>381</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><free/></availability><submitter name="Kevin Brubeck Unhammer" email="unhammer@fsfe.org"/><multilingual><language xml:lang="eng"/><language xml:lang="sme"/><language xml:lang="nob"/></multilingual><origFileName>http://www.samediggi.no/layout/set/print/Samedikki-birra/Organisasuvdnastruktuvra/Samediggeraddi/Sartnit-ja-artihkkalat/No-mining-in-Nussir-despite-area-development-plan-approval</origFileName><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p type="title" xml:lang="eng">No mining in Nussir despite area development plan approval</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">For more information, contact:</p>
<p>Sámediggi Executive Council member Silje Karine Muotka, + 47 984 87 576</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Member of Sámediggi Executive Council Silje Karine Muotka fears for the future of the environment and reindeer husbandry in Kvalsund now that Minister of Local Government and Modernisation Jan Tore Sanner has approved the area development plan for Nussir and Ulveryggen in Kvalsund Municipality in Finnmark County.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><span type="quote" xml:lang="eng">"I am not surprised, but I am nonetheless disappointed that Minister of Local Government and Modernisation Jan Tore Sanner would approve an area development plan for an activity that offers limited benefits to society at the same time as such a mine would have formidable adverse consequences on the environment, fishing and the reindeer husbandry"</span>, comments Sámediggi Executive Council member Silje Karine Muotka.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">"In his approval of the area development plan, the Minister assumes that no mining operations will take place before agreement has been reached with the reindeer husbandry industry about remedial measures. In addition to this, the plan would require the approval of the Norwegian Environment Agency and a licence from the mineral resources authorities would be required to operate a mine.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><span type="quote" xml:lang="eng">"The caveat that Nussir ASA must reach agreement with the reindeer husbandry industry regarding its initiatives is nonetheless positive, providing that a mining operation is not initiated without such agreement being reached. It is important that the reindeer husbandry industry does not feel pressured into something they cannot live with"</span>, continues Muotka. <span type="quote" xml:lang="eng">"Having said that, I find it strange that Minister Jan Tore Sanner so readily passes along the obligation under international law to ensure the livelihood of those in the reindeer husbandry to a mining company. The matter demonstrates how difficult it is for the Government to fulfil its commitments under international law in specific cases"</span>, comments Muotka.</p>
<p><span type="quote" xml:lang="eng">"I find it wrong and irresponsible to allow mining operations as planned in Nussir and Ulveryggen. Consequently, I will continue to strive to ensure that such operations do not come to fruition, and there will have to be several rounds with the authorities in the light of the Pollution Control Act, the Water Regulations and the Minerals Act"</span>, concludes Muotka.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">For more information, contact:</p>
<p>Sámediggi Executive Council member Silje Karine Muotka, + 47 984 87 576</p>
</body></document>
