<document xml:lang="sme" id="no_id"><header><title>Rádjegielddat nannejit ovttasbarggu - Sámi Siida rs</title><genre code="facta"/><author><unknown/></author><year>2010</year><wordcount>3058</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://www.samisiida.org/web/index.php?odas=44</origFileName><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><list><p type="listitem">Ovdasiidu</p>
<p type="listitem">Searvva miellahttun</p>
<p type="listitem">Min birra <list><p type="listitem">Oktavuođadieđut</p>
<p type="listitem">Stivra</p>
<p type="listitem">Njuolggadusat</p>
</list></p>
<p type="listitem">Arkiiva <list><p type="listitem">Beavdegirjjit</p>
<p type="listitem">Doaibmaplánat</p>
<p type="listitem">Doaibmamuitalusat</p>
<p type="listitem">Almmuhuheamit ja earát</p>
</list></p>
<p type="listitem">Ohcejoga báikenamat <list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="nob">Báikenamma DVD Rom</p>
</list></p>
<p type="listitem">Doaimmat <list><p type="listitem">Riekkesdoaibma</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="smj">Gollegiella</p>
</list></p>
<p type="listitem">Sápmi Talent <list><p type="listitem">Sápmi Talent</p>
<p type="listitem">Prográmma</p>
</list></p>
<p type="listitem">Ságastallan</p>
<p type="listitem">Govvagalleri</p>
</list><p>Registrere epoastačujuhusa vuostáiváldit ođasreivve ja dieđu go giinu cealká.</p>
<p>Govvagalleri</p>
<p>Sápmi Talent 2013</p>
<p>GOVVEN bargobáji govat</p>
<p>Jeagilveagi geasseleaira 8.-10.8.2012</p>
<p>Cavgil!</p>
<p>Čálit!</p>
<p>Rádjegielddat nannejit ovttasbarggu</p>
<p>Ohcejoga gielda ja Deanu gielda viiddidit dál skuvla- ja mánáidgárdeovttasbarggu riikkarájá rastá. “Dán lahkái mii beassat fállat buoret bálvalusaid iežamet ássiide,” dadjá Deanu gieldda sátnejođiheaddji  Frank Ingilæ.  “Suoma guovddášeiseválddit oidnet dákkár ovttasbarggu hui dehálažžan”, dadjá Ohcejoga gielddastivrra ságadoalli Veikko Guttorm.</p>
<p>Ohcejohnjálmmi skuvla ja Sirpmá skuvla leat guhkit áigge juo bargan ovttas.  Jagi 2005 rájes lea skuvllain leamaš oktasaš oahpahus guokte beaivvi vahkus.  Ohcejoga ja Deanu gielddat barget maiddái ovttas mánáidgárdefálaldagas (beaiveruoktofálaldagas).  Smávvámánát sáhttet oažžut sámegiel mánáidgárdefálaldaga nuppi riikkas.</p>
<p>Ovttasbarggus rájá rastá nannejuvvo sámegiel máhttu, daningo sámegiella doaibmá lunddolaš gulahallangiellan. Mánát ohppet maiddái bargat riikkaidgaskasaččat. Dát lea dehálaš gelbbolašvuohta globaliserejuvvon máilmmis.</p>
<p>Ohcejoga ja Deanu gielddat ovttas Deanu giellagáttiin áigot dál viiddidit dán ovttasbarggu.  Earret eará áigot ođđa prošeaktavirggi bokte bidjat johtui eambbo giellanannendoaimmaid skuvllain ja mánáidgárddiin.  Árramánnávuođa bajásgeassima áššedovdi doaimma čadnojuvvo Ohcejoga sámi beaiveruktui (mánáidgárdái).  Ohcanáigemearrin lea 6.5.10.</p>
<p>Sosiála- ja dearvvasvuođaministeria lea juolludan Ohcejoga gildii Kaste-prográmma mielde stáhtadoarjaga Deanuleagi sosiála- dearvvasvuođabálvalusaid ovddidanfidnui. Dáinna fidnuin nannejuvvo sosiála- ja dearvvasvuođabálvalusaid doaibman Suoma ja Norgga rájá badjel. Minister Paula Risikko atná dán máŋggabealat ovttasbarggu rájá badjel hui deaŧalažžan.</p>
<p>Loga eambbo prošeavttas “OVTTAS! Sámi giella-, skuvla-, ja mánáidgárdeovddideapmi Deanuleagis" dás .</p>
<p>Cealkke</p>
<p xml:lang="kal">Namma*</p>
<p>Čujuhus dahje epoasta</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Váldoteaksta*</p>
<p xml:lang="sma">FD36rvJkofu</p>
<p xml:lang="est">MumVG3rSu 27.10.2015</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Excellent take on the situation, Chuck. I coludn"t agree with you more. Maybe maybe this drastic change in Macworld Expo isn"t such a terrible thing. The cost savings and there must be a huge cost savings for Apple seems like a spart business move. With Apple stores all over the world and Appl</p>
<p xml:lang="fkv">CJ6GWToko</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">H0W3SMwT 14.02.2017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Alway love white on Kraft your card is awesome Becky love the stamp set …just arrived but haven’t inked it up yet cause i’m too busy blog hopping ha ha! Already a foye2wlro30;leah another fun hop!</p>
<p xml:lang="fkv">CJ6GWToko</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">H0W3SMwT 14.02.2017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Alway love white on Kraft your card is awesome Becky love the stamp set …just arrived but haven’t inked it up yet cause i’m too busy blog hopping ha ha! Already a foye2wlro30;leah another fun hop!</p>
<p xml:lang="smj">rUitj32gqw</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">JfzTbsANw 14.02.2017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The voice of ratyinaloti! Good to hear from you.</p>
<p xml:lang="smj">rUitj32gqw</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">JfzTbsANw 14.02.2017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The voice of ratyinaloti! Good to hear from you.</p>
<p xml:lang="smj">rUitj32gqw</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">JfzTbsANw 14.02.2017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The voice of ratyinaloti! Good to hear from you.</p>
<p>Vástit dán cealkámuii</p>
<p xml:lang="sma">FD36rvJkofu</p>
<p xml:lang="est">MumVG3rSu 27.10.2015</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Excellent take on the situation, Chuck. I coludn"t agree with you more. Maybe maybe this drastic change in Macworld Expo isn"t such a terrible thing. The cost savings and there must be a huge cost savings for Apple seems like a spart business move. With Apple stores all over the world and Apple"s other marketing efforts, do they really need exposure to a relatively small group of people who happen to make it to the show? I"m sure someone can argue that at least 75% of those who attend Macworld Expo are already sold on the Mac. There are four (or maybe five?) Apple stores in Arizona alone. Surely the same number of people pass through those Apple stores in a single day as what pass through the Apple booth at a Macworld Expo during the few days of the show.And here"s one example of how Macworld is hurting Apple I"m desperate for a replacement for my 12 PowerBook. I have a 15 MacBook Pro but want something much smaller and ligher with build in DVD to take on the road. This recent wave of laptops almost convinced me to invest in a 13 PowerBook. Almost. But because Macworld Exp is around the corner and because Apple usually has something new at each show, I decided to wait to see if my dream computer will be released there. If there was no anticipation of a Macworld announcement, I would have bought the new computer last week. (And I am still hopeful that I"ll get my tiny Mac laptop someday.)There"s only one good-sized group that will really suffer from this: medium and small developers. They"re losing out on their opportunity to show off their products to a captive audience. They"re losing the ability to get one-on-one face time with potential customers. All of this was pointed out during the MacJury episode we recorded the other day. It makes good listening for anyone interested in how an insider feels about what"s going on.But there are other ways for developers to get attention for their products and other ways for them to interact with customers. The change or possible demise of Macworld Expo might bring about the dawn of a new day or an evolution style survival of the fittest for developers who depended on Macworld Expo to generate interest in their products.Anyway, good take on the situation. I think I pretty much agree with everything you have to say.</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">1eSM6JRAD</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">tw16Nj0C 14.02.2017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Thanks for giving us a spin. We apcitpraee it. Do let us know your feedback when you receive your HotBook. Also, just to let you know we had huge amount of traffic over the weekend. Do give us a try again. HotPrints</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">1eSM6JRAD</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">tw16Nj0C 14.02.2017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Thanks for giving us a spin. We apcitpraee it. Do let us know your feedback when you receive your HotBook. Also, just to let you know we had huge amount of traffic over the weekend. Do give us a try again. HotPrints</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">P4p6ky2n</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">cdFjHDKKVZ 14.02.2017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Just the type of inihgst we need to fire up the debate.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">P4p6ky2n</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">cdFjHDKKVZ 14.02.2017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Just the type of inihgst we need to fire up the debate.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">P4p6ky2n</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">cdFjHDKKVZ 14.02.2017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Just the type of inihgst we need to fire up the debate.</p>
<p>Vástit dán cealkámuii</p>
<p xml:lang="sma">FD36rvJkofu</p>
<p xml:lang="est">MumVG3rSu 27.10.2015</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Excellent take on the situation, Chuck. I coludn"t agree with you more. Maybe maybe this drastic change in Macworld Expo isn"t such a terrible thing. The cost savings and there must be a huge cost savings for Apple seems like a spart business move. With Apple stores all over the world and Apple"s other marketing efforts, do they really need exposure to a relatively small group of people who happen to make it to the show? I"m sure someone can argue that at least 75% of those who attend Macworld Expo are already sold on the Mac. There are four (or maybe five?) Apple stores in Arizona alone. Surely the same number of people pass through those Apple stores in a single day as what pass through the Apple booth at a Macworld Expo during the few days of the show.And here"s one example of how Macworld is hurting Apple I"m desperate for a replacement for my 12 PowerBook. I have a 15 MacBook Pro but want something much smaller and ligher with build in DVD to take on the road. This recent wave of laptops almost convinced me to invest in a 13 PowerBook. Almost. But because Macworld Exp is around the corner and because Apple usually has something new at each show, I decided to wait to see if my dream computer will be released there. If there was no anticipation of a Macworld announcement, I would have bought the new computer last week. (And I am still hopeful that I"ll get my tiny Mac laptop someday.)There"s only one good-sized group that will really suffer from this: medium and small developers. They"re losing out on their opportunity to show off their products to a captive audience. They"re losing the ability to get one-on-one face time with potential customers. All of this was pointed out during the MacJury episode we recorded the other day. It makes good listening for anyone interested in how an insider feels about what"s going on.But there are other ways for developers to get attention for their products and other ways for them to interact with customers. The change or possible demise of Macworld Expo might bring about the dawn of a new day or an evolution style survival of the fittest for developers who depended on Macworld Expo to generate interest in their products.Anyway, good take on the situation. I think I pretty much agree with everything you have to say.</p>
<p>Vástit dán cealkámuii</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">BcLuWe4Vw</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">7Crhs2AxnY 28.10.2015</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">What"s a day in your life like A day in my life wouldn"t be coetlmpe without seeing my daughter smile..and now..without feeling my little boy ( hoping it would be a boy) move inside my tummy. And of course, without feeling the warmth of my husband"s touch.My day starts with a goodmorning mama and good morning kalel ( her baby brother in my tummy) , a pretty cute smile with a simple question of do you have something for me? I simple no will make her shrug her shoulders and say its OK but a big yes can really make her jump with joy! Be it a simple candy..to as big as a good book or a happy or kiddie meal with a toy of course!And then the routine, breakfast to lunch taking a bath together the 4 of us.. papa, mama, kim and kalel in my tummy a nap in the afternoon if I don"t have office and we"ll all play together, my daughter being the cook/chef and us parents, the customers she needs to satisfy.Our nights ends with our kulitan, sweet family hugs and kisses, caressing my baby boy in the tummy and of course, a prayer that is lead by our Ate Kim. fyi..I"am only</p>
<p>Vástit dán cealkámuii</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">BcLuWe4Vw</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">7Crhs2AxnY 28.10.2015</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">What"s a day in your life like A day in my life wouldn"t be coetlmpe without seeing my daughter smile..and now..without feeling my little boy ( hoping it would be a boy) move inside my tummy. And of course, without feeling the warmth of my husband"s touch.My day starts with a goodmorning mama and good morning kalel ( her baby brother in my tummy) , a pretty cute smile with a simple question of do you have something for me? I simple no will make her shrug her shoulders and say its OK but a big yes can really make her jump with joy! Be it a simple candy..to as big as a good book or a happy or kiddie meal with a toy of course!And then the routine, breakfast to lunch taking a bath together the 4 of us.. papa, mama, kim and kalel in my tummy a nap in the afternoon if I don"t have office and we"ll all play together, my daughter being the cook/chef and us parents, the customers she needs to satisfy.Our nights ends with our kulitan, sweet family hugs and kisses, caressing my baby boy in the tummy and of course, a prayer that is lead by our Ate Kim. fyi..I"am only two months pregnant, would you believe that my daughter actually believes that she has her baby BROTHER in my tummy for the meantime, So be IT!</p>
<p xml:lang="est">6e4Pcs3VqWXp</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">bGYOtnfNL 27.12.2015</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">I am so sorry for your loss. Even when you are expecting it, it is still hard. The first week is the haesrdt in my experience. Just try to distract yourself and cry when you need to. Sam was an adorable and cheerful little dude and we all know that you gave him a good life. He was part of your family. My advice is to keep his things but put them out of sight for now. Create a memorial of some kind. My dog Agnes died in October and I still haven"t put together hers but I have photos and her collar to use. Best wishes for you in this difficult time.</p>
<p xml:lang="est">6e4Pcs3VqWXp</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">bGYOtnfNL 27.12.2015</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">I am so sorry for your loss. Even when you are expecting it, it is still hard. The first week is the haesrdt in my experience. Just try to distract yourself and cry when you need to. Sam was an adorable and cheerful little dude and we all know that you gave him a good life. He was part of your family. My advice is to keep his things but put them out of sight for now. Create a memorial of some kind. My dog Agnes died in October and I still haven"t put together hers but I have photos and her collar to use. Best wishes for you in this difficult time.</p>
<p xml:lang="est">6e4Pcs3VqWXp</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">bGYOtnfNL 27.12.2015</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">I am so sorry for your loss. Even when you are expecting it, it is still hard. The first week is the haesrdt in my experience. Just try to distract yourself and cry when you need to. Sam was an adorable and cheerful little dude and we all know that you gave him a good life. He was part of your family. My advice is to keep his things but put them out of sight for now. Create a memorial of some kind. My dog Agnes died in October and I still haven"t put together hers but I have photos and her collar to use. Best wishes for you in this difficult time.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">kN42pkeg</p>
<p xml:lang="hbs">uXl4XeBpO 28.12.2015</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">I am so SO sorry, Cleo. Even an expected death is heart-wrenching. And, beuacse of you, we all are mourning the loss of Sam (which is how it should be, beuacse Sam = AWESOMESAUCE). And, IMO, the death of a pet is somehow just a little more painful than the death of a human. I"ve never been able to figure out why that is. Know that your family is in my prayers and Sam is already hanging out with St. Francis in the giant field of frolicking in the sky.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">kN42pkeg</p>
<p xml:lang="hbs">uXl4XeBpO 28.12.2015</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">I am so SO sorry, Cleo. Even an expected death is heart-wrenching. And, beuacse of you, we all are mourning the loss of Sam (which is h</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">kN42pkeg</p>
<p xml:lang="hbs">uXl4XeBpO 28.12.2015</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">I am so SO sorry, Cleo. Even an expected death is heart-wrenching. And, beuacse of you, we all are mourning the loss of Sam (which is how it should be, beuacse Sam = AWESOMESAUCE). And, IMO, the death of a pet is somehow just a little more painful than the death of a human. I"ve never been able to figure out why that is. Know that your family is in my prayers and Sam is already hanging out with St. Francis in the giant field of frolicking in the sky.</p>
<p>Vástit dán cealkámuii</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">s6aTQha7</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">RVG9aCJDMg 14.02.2017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">April — Thanks for your comment!You may not like what I’m going to say, but I would avoid it for the same reasons I’d avoid powdered milk. First, the drying process pasteurizes and completely kills any of the benefits of the buttermilk culture (enzymes, probiotics, etc.). It’s also likely to create free glutamates (another name for MS8G)You.217;d be substituting a living, health-promoting food for a dead, harmful food.In my book, it’s just not worth it.</p>
<p>Vástit dán cealkámuii</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">s6aTQha7</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">RVG9aCJDMg 14.02.2017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">April — Thanks for your comment!You may not like what I’m going to say, but I would avoid it for the same reasons I’d avoid powdered milk. First, the drying process pasteurizes and completely kills any of the benefits of the buttermilk culture (enzymes, probiotics, etc.). It’s also likely to create free glutamates (another name for MS8G)You.217;d be substituting a living, health-promoting food for a dead, harmful food.In my book, it’s just not worth it.</p>
<p>Vástit dán cealkámuii</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">K4DyQfPBg1W</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">81S3mhC4 14.02.2017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">I really apeiacrpte free, succinct, reliable data like this.</p>
<p>Vástit dán cealkámuii</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">K4DyQfPBg1W</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">81S3mhC4 14.02.2017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">I really apeiacrpte free, succinct, reliable data like this.</p>
<p>Vástit dán cealkámuii</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">K4DyQfPBg1W</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">81S3mhC4 14.02.2017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">I really apeiacrpte free, succinct, reliable data like this.</p>
<p>Vástit dán cealkámuii</p>
</body></document>