<document xml:lang="sme" id="no_id"><header><title>Inclusive Journalism | Sámi allaskuvla</title><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>297</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://samas.no/se/a/inclusive-journalism</origFileName><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="eng">Seminar and Workshop</p>
<p>02. skábmamánu, 09:00  - 03. skábmamánu, 18:00</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="eng">Inclusive Journalism</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="eng">Sámi University College, Guovdageaidnu/Kautokeino, Norway, 2-3 November 2015</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="deu">PROGRAMME</p>
<p xml:lang="isl"><em type="italic">Sunday 1.11 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nob">09.00 Departure to Karasjok</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">10.30-12.00 Sámi National Museum and Sámi Collection, guided by Margarete Vars</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">15.00 Return from Karasjok, possibility to visit Sámi handicraft shops in Kautokeino</p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="italic">Monday 2.11 </em>Morning 10.00-10.10 Greeting, Rector Gunvor Guttorm 10.10-10.30 Sámi legal and social status, Dr Nils Johan Päiviö, Sámi University College 10.30-10.50 The media landscape in the Sámi region, Dr Lia Markelin, Sámi University College </p>
<p xml:lang="est">10-50-11.10 Pause</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">11.10-11.30 Sámi media history, Associate Professor Arne Johansen Ijäs 11.30-11.50 Sámi media use, Dr Torkel Rasmussen, Sámi University College</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">11.50-12.15 Discussion</p>
<p xml:lang="deu"><em type="italic">Lunch </em></p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Afternoon</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">14.00-14.20 Framing Inclusive Journalism: Between Necessary Idealism and Depressing Realism, Prof. Charlies Husband, Bradford University and Sámi University College</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">14.20-14.40 Journalism and Shadow Publics, Prof. Verica Rupar, AUT University, Auckland 14.40-15.00 Discussion</p>
<p xml:lang="est">15.00-15.15 Pause</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">15.15-15.45 Maori Broadcasting and Self-Determination, Adjunct Fellow Jane Huria (Ngāi Tahu) and Prof. Donald Matheson, University of Canterbury</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">15.45-16.05 Internationalization of higher education: the Inclusive Journalism Initiative, Head of International Department Inger Munk and Associate Prof. Inger K. Larsen, Danish School of Media and Journalism, Århus</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">16.05-16.25 Inclusive Journalism from a pedagogical perspective, Prof. Tom Moring, University of Helsinki and Sámi University College</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">16.25-17.00 Discussion</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">18.00 Buffet dinner offered by the Sámi University College</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Dinner speech by the Dean Johan Strömgren</p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="italic">Tuesday 3.11 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Morning</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">09.00-09.30 New realism in photography and film, Prof. Tytti Soila, Stockholm University</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">09.30-09.45 Discussion</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">10.00-13.00 Two parallel sessions: Indigenous Journalism Master's Programme student presentations in two workshops (the senior participants will serve as discussants) (rooms 02101 and 02102)</p>
<p xml:lang="deu"><em type="italic">Lunch </em></p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Afternoon 14.00-17.00 IJI Article workshop (for the article authors, the Journalism lecture room) Guided tour to the Tundra (weather permitting)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">18.00 Free evening activities (Pizza party at the Student House)</p>
</body></document>
