<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<tmx>
  <header segtype="sentence" o-tmf="OmegaT TMX" adminlang="en-US" srclang="sme" datatype="plaintext">
    <prop type="x-filename">index2.php_option=com_content_task=view_id=951_lang=davvi.html.xml</prop>
  </header>
  <body>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Greenland Eyes - filbmafestivála Sajosis 20.-24.11.2014</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>International Film festival Greenland eyes comes to Finland on its Nordic tour in November.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Riikkaidgaskasaš filbmafestivála Greenland Eyes boahtá Supmii Davviriikkaid turnees skábmamánus.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>The festival brings the colors, sounds and atmosphere of Greenland to Sajos on 20th-24th of November.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Oaidninláhkai leat oanehisfilmmat, animašuvnnat, dokumeanttat, musihkkavideot, historjjálaš potreahtat ja unihka guhkes filmmat nu ruonáeatnanlaš go olgoriikkalaš bagadalliin.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>The festival will showcase a range of shorts, animations, documentaries, music videos and unique feature length productions both from Greenlandic and foreign film directors.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Greenland Eyes lea máilmmi stuorámus Ruonáeatnamii gulavaš festivála.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>Greenland eyes is the biggest festival focusing on Greenland.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Dat buktá ovdan filmmaid, mat ovddastit sierra genreid ja sierra áigodagaid. Oktasaš filmmaide lea dat, ahte dat muitalit midjiide juoiddá dálá Ruonáeatnamis.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>It features films across all genres each film selected to add an individual insight into today ’ s Greenland.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Festivála lágiduvvo dál nuppe geardde.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>The festival is organized for the second time.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Festivála vuosttas jagi 2012 filmmain návddašuvvui Berliinis. Dán jage filmmaid mearri lea lassánan nu olu ja beroštupmi leamašan nu viiddis, ahte ovtta gávpoga sajis festivála johtá dál buot Davviriikkaid.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>The inaugural festival took place in Berlin in 2012 and this year the number of submitted films was so great, and the interest so overwhelming, that the 2014 festival is touring all the Nordic countries.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Borgemánus Ruonáeatnamis álgán festiválaturnee lea ovdal Suoma geargan juo Dánmárkui, Fearasulluide, Islándai ja Ruŧŧii. Suoma maŋŋá maŋimuš čájeheamit dollojit Norggas juovlamánu 18. beaivve.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>Beginning in Greenland on August the 28 th the festival then travels to Denmark, Faroe Islands, Iceland, Sweden and Finland, before finishing in Norway on December the 18 th.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Filmmat čájehuvvojit Sámekulturguovddáš Sajosa auditorios.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>The screenings takes place in the auditorium of Sámi Cultural Center Sajos.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Filmmaide lea eaŋgalsgielat teaksta.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>All the films have subtitles in English.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Prográmma:</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>Thursday 20.11.2014 at 18.00</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Duorastat 20.11.2014 dmu 18.00 Festivála rahpansánit: festivála hoavda Ivalo Frank ja buvttadeaddji Nicholas Alan.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>Introduction by festival director &amp;producer Ivalo Frank and Nicholas Alan.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Filbma Nuummioq (Someone from Nuuk bag.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>At 18.00 Greenland Unrealised (by Dania Reymond) and</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Otto Rosing ja Torben Beck)</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>At 20.00 Anigaaq (by Jonas Cuaron) and</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Lávvardat 22.11.2014 dmu 11.00 Filmmat The girl and the dogs (bag.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>Saturday 22.11.2014</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Guillaume Mainguet ja Selma Vihunen) ja Souls in a room (The making of an album) bag. Mikisoq H. Lynge) sihke Echoes (bag.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>At 11.00 The girl and the dogs (by Guillaume Mainguet and Selma Vihunen) and Souls in a room (The making of an album) by Mikisoq H. Lynge) and Echoes (by Ivalo Frank).</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Ivalo Frank).</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>Q &amp;A with director.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Maŋimuš filmma loahpas lea maiddái gažaldat - vástádus – sessio bagadalliin. dmu 17.30 Camera Borealis &amp; Kaamosjazz konsearta Guhkkin Davvin – Mátki lundui govaiguin ja šuoŋaiguin.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>At 17.30 Kaamos Jazz and Camera Borealis presents: Picture concert ” Faraway in North – A journey into nature ” at Sámi cultural centre Sajos.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Sotnabeaivi 23.11.2014 dmu 18.00 Filbma Sullorsuaq (The tunnel bag. Marc Fussing Rosbach) ja Hinnarik Sinnattunilu (Hinnariks ’ s dreams bag.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>At 18.00 Sullorsuaq (The tunnel by Marc Fussing Rosbach) and Hinnarik Sinnattunilu (Hinnariks ’ s dreams by Angajo Lennert Sandgreen)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Martin Skinkløv ja Rune Bundgaard)</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>Monday 24.11.2014</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Vuossárga 24.11.2014 dmu 18.00 Filbma Aulahuliat (Moving Images by Uusaqqak Qujaukitsag) ja Block P (by Peter Jensen ja Rikke Diemer) dmu 20.00 Sooqakersuuttugut (Why we fight bag.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>At 20.00 Sooqakersuuttugut (Why we fight by Inuk Silis Hoegh) Before tomorrow (by Marie Hélène Cousineau and Madeline Ivalu)</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Inuk Silis Hoegh) Before tomorrow (bag.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>Information about the films on the festival homepage.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Marie Hélène Cousineau ja Madeline Ivalu) Bileahtaid filmmaide sáhttá oastit Sajosa infos Sajosa rabasáigge ja maiddái neahttagávppis www.lipputoimisto.fi.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>Tickets for the movies from Sajos info during opening times (Mon-Fri 9am-5pm) and from the internet www.lipputoimisto.fi.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Dan lassin dat vuvdojit diimmu ovdal juohke filmma álgima uvssa luhtte.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>In addition tickets can be bought from the door one hour before the screening.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Bileahtat 6 euro, nuorat (vuollái 17 jagi) ja studeanttat 3 euro ja mánát (vuollái 12 jagi) nuvttá.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>Tickets for the movies 6 euros. Youth (under 17) and students (3 e) and children (under 12) free of charge.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Kaamosjazz-konseartta bileahtaid sáhttá oastit bileahttadoaimmahagas www.lipputoimisto.fi dahje Sajosa infos rabasáigge.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>The tickets for the Kaamosjazz &amp; Camera Borealis – concert can be bought from www.lipputoimisto.fi or from Sajos info.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Dan lassin dat vuvdojit diimmu ovdal dáhpáhusa álgima uvssa luhtte.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>Tickets can also be bought from the door an hour before the show.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Ovdabileahtta 25 e / uvssas 30 euro.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>Pre-ticket 25e/30 from the door.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>Festivála áigge Sajosa váldofeaskáris lea oaidninláhkai čuovgagovvačájáhus ISI.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>Photography exhibition ISI.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>/ EYE.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>/ EYE.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>/ ØJE, gosa Pipaluk Lykke Løstrup lea čohkken amatevragovvideaddjiid digigovaid miehtá máilmmi.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>/ ØJE during the festivals in the lobby of Sajos.</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>dahje telefovnnain 0045 36 96 56 62 Lassidieđut bileahtain: Tämä sähköpostiosoite on suojattu roskapostia vastaan, aseta javascripttuki päälle nähdäksesi osoitteen.</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>This e-mail address is being protected from spam bots, you need JavaScript enabled to view it or by phone 0045 36 96 56 62</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
    <tu>
      <tuv xml:lang="sme">
        <seg>dahje telefovnnain 050 565 1346</seg>
      </tuv>
      <tuv xml:lang="eng">
        <seg>This e-mail address is being protected from spam bots, you need JavaScript enabled to view it or by phone +358 50 565 1346</seg>
      </tuv>
    </tu>
  </body>
</tmx>
