<document xml:lang="sme" id="no_id"><header><title>ođđa girji/New book</title><genre code="blogs"/><author><person firstname="Rauna" lastname="Kuokkanen" sex="f" born="" nationality="FI"/></author><year>2009</year><wordcount>388</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>http://rauna.net/2009/12/15/odda-girjinew-book/</origFileName><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 150288 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="eng">Skip to content</p>
<p type="title">ođđa girji/New book</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Posted on</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">by rauna</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Posted in rauna's posts in english , Sámegillii</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tagged sámedutkan , Sami research</p>
<p>Mu ođđa girji, <em type="italic">Boares dego eana: Eamiálbmogiid diehtu, filosofiijat ja dutkan </em>lea almmustuvvan gieskat ja dan sáhttá diŋgot ČálliidLágádusas. Girji lea vuosttas sámegielat láidehus eamiálbmotdutkamuššii ja dieđu, dutkama ja oahpahusa dekoloniseremii. Girji čilge dáid vuođđodoahpagiid ja -fáttáid ja ovdamearkkaid bokte buktá ovdan makkár áššit leat guovddážis go lea sáhka eamiálbmogiid dieđus, diehtoortnegiin, filosofiijain ja eamiálbmogiid dutkanmetodologiijain. Girji čilge maiddái eamiálbmotdutkama konteavstta ja historjjá – dan manne eamiálbmotdutkit leat oaidnan dárbbu buktit oidnosii ja deattuhit eamiálbmogiid dieđu, jurddašeami ja dutkanvugiid dehálašvuođa. Girjji ovdamearkkat leat iešguđet eamiálbmogiin, muhto seammás girji guorahallá, mo dáid ovdamearkkaid sáhttá vejolaččat heivehit sámi diliide dahje váldit málle dain. </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">My new book, <em type="italic">Boaris dego eana. Eamiálbmogiid diehtu, filosofiijat ja dutkan </em>(As Old as the Earth. Indigenous Knowledge, Philosophies and Research) has been published by a Sami publisher ČálliidLágádus in its new Sami Academica series. It is the first book-length study on indigenous knowledge, philosophies and research in the Sami language. Drawing on indigenous, feminist, postcolonial and poststructural theories, the book discusses the emergence and significance of indigenous scholarship in the context of decolonizing indigenous systems of knowing. It critically considers the concepts of knowledge, knowledge production, philosophies, research methodologies, ethics and traditional/modern dichotomies in indigenous scholarship and examines the ways in which these considerations are relevant in and relate to Sami research. The book provides extensive examples of indigenous knowledge and research particularly from North America, Australia and New Zealand as well as in the Sami context. </p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="eng">Share this:</p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="eng">Click to share on Twitter (Opens in new window)</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="eng">Click to share on Facebook (Opens in new window)</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="eng">Click to share on Google+ (Opens in new window)</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="eng">Click to email this to a friend (Opens in new window)</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="eng">Click to share on LinkedIn (Opens in new window)</p>
</list><p type="title" xml:lang="eng">Related</p>
<p type="title" xml:lang="eng">3 thoughts on <span type="quote">“ođđa girji/New book”</span></p>
<list><p type="listitem" xml:lang="mdf"><list/></p>
</list><p type="title" xml:lang="eng">Leave a Reply Cancel reply</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Your email address will not be published.  Required fields are marked *</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Comment</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Name *</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Email *</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Website</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Notify me of follow-up comments by email.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Notify me of new posts by email.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Send to Email Address</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Your Name</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Your Email Address</p>
<p xml:lang="tur">Cancel</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Post was not sent - check your email addresses!</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Email check failed, please try again</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Sorry, your blog cannot share posts by email.</p>
</body></document>
